L. C. Dunn Papers ca.1920-1974 Mss.B.D917
American Philosophical Society
L. C. Dunn Papers
ca. 1920-1974
Mss.B.D917
American Philosophical Society
15.5 Linear feet
L.C. Dunn was one of the most significant figures in the emerging field of developmental genetics in the 20th century. His T-locus work with the mouse established a number of important genetic principles, including ideas of gene interaction, the distribution of alleles in wild populations, and the factors that influence fertility. He wrote an important textbook of genetics, Principles of Genetics (1925), in collaboration with Sinnott (and later Dobzhansky); other significant books authored or co-authored by him include Heredity, Race and Society (1946), and A Short History of Genetics (1965). He worked in poultry genetics for eight years at the Agricultural Experiment Station in Storrs, CT, from 1920-1928. The remainder of his career was spent at Columbia University, where he worked with rats, mice, and fruit flies, and proved himself to be an inspiring teacher as well. His interest in international scientific collaboration led him to establish ties to Soviet scientists, and to help relocate refugee scientists during World War II. He remained active in his profession to the end of his life. This collection includes correspondence, reports, notebooks, lectures, and photographs. It is a rich collection, documenting the development of American genetics as well as Dunn's interests in humanitarian efforts and international affairs. There is significant material relating to American-U.S.S.R. contacts, particularly in the files on the American-Soviet Friendship Council and the American-Soviet Science Society. There is much, as well, on the impact of the Lysenko controversy in the U. S. Dunn's inerestt in European scientists can also be seen in the sizable amount of material on the Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced German Scholars. Material relating to the Kilgore and Magnusson bills for the support of science (predecessors to the NSF) are also in the collection. Of note are data on the following: National Research Council Committee on Experimental Animals and Plants; research on the population study of the Jewish community in Rome; and Columbia University. There is much in the correspondence concerning Drosophila, poultry genetics, and other such topics; Walter Landauer is Dunn's major correspondent.
Dunn, L. C., (Leslie Clarence), 1893-1974
Bibliography
Allen, Garland E., "Leslie Clarence Dunn (November 2, 1893-March 19, 1974)," Folia Mendeliana 10 (Brno: Mendelianum Musei Moraviae, 1975).
Dobzhansky, Theodosius, "Leslie Clarence Dunn: November 2, 1893-March 19, 1974," Biographical Memoirs 49 (Washington: National Academy of Sciences, 1978).
Other Finding Aids note
The Dunn Papers are also described in Bentley Glass' A Guide to the Genetics Collections of the American Philosophical Society.
Related Archival Materials note
The American Philosophical Society Library's printed materials collection holds copies of most of Dunn's major titles, in addition to many of his minor titles, articles, and pamphlets. For further information about Dunn's published writings held by the APS, please consult the printed materials card catalog.
Additional Dunn correspondence can be found in the Caspari Papers (71 letters), Davenport Papers (57 letters), Dobzhansky Papers (31 letters), Lerner Papers (21 letters), and Stern Papers (130 letters).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired 1967-1974; gift of Dr. L.C. Dunn.
Scope and Contents note
The Dunn Papers are a major resource for the study of the history of genetics during the critical quarter century between 1930 and 1955. From his perch at Columbia, Dunn was well situated to take part in the sweeping changes in the field, and was deeply involved in the debates over the social implications of genetic thought. The collection includes a full suite of correspondence, reports, notebooks, lectures, and photographs documenting the development of American genetics as well as Dunn's interests in humanitarian efforts and international affairs.
The Dunn Papers are rich in material relating to American-Soviet scientific contacts, particularly in the files on the American-Soviet Friendship Council and the American-Soviet Science Society. There is much, as well, on the impact of the Lysenko controversy in the United States, and Dunn's interest in European scientists can also be seen in the sizable quantity of material on the Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced German Scholars. Material relating to the Kilgore and Magnusson bills for the support of science (predecessors to the National Science Foundation) are also in the collection.
Of note are data on the following: National Research Council Committee on Experimental Animals and Plants; research on the population study of the Jewish community in Rome; and files of material concerning Columbia University, where he spent most of his academic career. There is much in the correspondence concerning Drosophila, poultry genetics, and other such topics. Volumetrically and, to a degree, scientifically, Dunn's major correspondent was Walter Landauer (ca. 1.5 linear feet); other correspondents include A. F. Blakeslee, Franz Boas, Kristine Bonnevie, Calvin B. Bridges, Alexis Carrel, Ernst Caspari, William E. Castle, Alfred E. Cohn, George W. Corner, Gunnar Dahlberg, Charles H. Danforth, Paul R. David, Milislav Demerec, Theodosius Dobzhansky, Boris Ephrussi, Ronald A. Fisher, Irene Geyer-Duszynska, Richard Goldschmidt, Emil J. Gumbel, Sir Julian Huxley, Hugo Iltis, Pavol Ivanyi, Herbert S. Jennings, Victor Jollas, Karl Landsteiner, Richard C. Lewontin, Otto L. Mohr, Tove Mohr, Thomas H. Morgan, Herman J. Muller, Curt Stern, and Edwin B. Wilson.
Series I Correspondence, ca.1920-1974 (26 boxes; 13 linear feet)
Series II Oral history transcripts, 1958-1960 (2 boxes; 1.5 linear feet)
Series III Reprints, 1942-1973 (11 folders; 0.25 linear feet)
Series IV Genetics editorial correspondence, 1935-1949 (2 boxes; 1.0 linear foot)
Series V Research, 1953-1968 (2 boxes; 1 linear foot)
Series VI Photographs, 1911-1974 (1 box; 0.5 linear feet)
Biographical/Historical note
L.C. Dunn was a seminal figure in the 20th century emergence of developmental genetics. His T-locus work with the mouse established a number of important genetic principles, including ideas of gene interaction, the distribution of alleles in wild populations, and the factors that influence fertility, and his influence spread, in part, through his widely used genetics textbook, Principles of Genetics (N.Y.: McGraw Hill, 1925), written in collaboration with Edmund Ware Sinnott (and later Theodosius Dobzhansky). Other significant works authored or co-authored by Dunn include Heredity, Race and Society (1946), and A Short History of Genetics (1965).
Leslie Clarence Dunn was born in Buffalo, New York in 1893, the son of Clarence Leslie and Mary Eliza (Booth) Dunn. At Dartmouth College from 1911-1915, he applied himself to the study of zoology under John H. Gerould, with whom he maintained life-long ties. It was through Gerould that he obtained a copy of T.H. Morgan's Heredity and Sex in 1914, a book that significantly influenced the course of Dunn's professional career. Smitten with genetics, after graduating from Dartmouth, Dunn applied to study under Morgan at Columbia University, but was turned away from the already overcrowded fly lab. Instead, he took an assistantship to work with William E. Castle at Harvard, where he was assigned charge of the laboratory for breeding Drosophila. His first significant work was a study of sex-linked genes in Drosophila, but when his results were "scooped" by a student of Morgan, he turned to work on linked genes in mice and rats. He published eight papers on rodent genetics between 1916 and 1921, including his dissertation Linkage in Mice and Rats (1920).
Dunn's graduate work was interrupted by the outbreak of the First World War, during which he was commissioned as a First Lieutenant in the American Expeditionary Force in France. He married Louise Porter, a Smith College graduate, in 1918, with whom he had two sons, Robert Leslie (b.1921) and Stephen Porter (b.1928).
After his release from the Army, Dunn's first professional position was serving as poultry geneticist at the Agricultural Experiment Station in Storrs, Connecticut. His time there (1920-1928) was productive, resulting in over forty papers on poultry genetics as well as the first edition of Principles of Genetics. One of the most widely used genetics textbooks of its time, it went into five editions and was translated into numerous foreign languages.
In 1929, Dunn was tapped by Columbia to fill the post vacated by Morgan, who had departed for the California Institute of Technology. As a full professor in the Zoology Department, Dunn quickly demonstrated his abilities as a teacher as well as a researcher, mentoring Simone Gluecksohn-Waelsch and Dorothea Bennett, among many others.
Because life in the heart of New York City precluded large-scale research projects on poultry, Dunn revived his research on rodents and fruit flies, although he continued to keep hand in poultry, working in concert with Walter Landauer at Storrs. Initially, Dunn's mouse work at Columbia focussed on the problem of the inheritance of pigmentation, but his interest in congenital abnormalities soon led him to branch out into a study of lethal and semi-lethal mutants in research animals and compare them to similar conditions in humans. His work on T-locus mutants occupied over forty years and established him as a leader in developmental genetics. His research also verged on population genetics: he studied colonies of mice in both the laboratory and the field, establishing the principle that gametic selection could be even more powerful than natural selection.
Possessed of a strong social conscience honed by association with his fellow Columbians Theodosius Dobzhansky and Franz Boas, Dunn took an active interest in human genetics and its social implications. During the 1920s and 1930s, he spoke out against the misapplication of genetics to justify mistreatment of oppressed groups of people, including blacks and Jews. He established an Institute for the Study of Human Variation at Columbia in the 1950s. Although the Institute was short-lived, several key research projects resulted from it, including Dunn's "The Jewish Community in Rome." The Institute also spawned a number of students who have made important contributions to human genetics, including R. H. Osborne and W. S. Pollitzer.
In 1946, Dunn and Theodosius Dobzhansky collaborated on Heredity, Race, and Society, an immensely important book that cast a genetist's eye on the race problem in America. Taking cues from the work of Ashley Montagu, Franz Boas, and others, the work was an important study of racial variation, but also a major statement on the vexing question coopted by eugenicists of the relationship between nature and nurture. "We come into the world," they wrote, "as a bundle of possibilities bequeathed to us by our parents and other ancestors. Our nurture comes from the world about us. What happens to the nurture that comes in depends, however, on the nature that receives it." Dunn and Dobzhansky concluded that nature and nurture were inseparably intertwined and integral to the shaping of human capacities, rendering the dichotomy between them not only misleading, but fundamentally wrong. In 1951 Dunn was selected to write the UNESCO report Race and Biology, which carried this point further.
Dunn's personal friendships with scientists and their families from around the world often served as a springboard into other activities. During a tour of Europe in 1927, for example, Dunn visited Russia as the guest of A.S. Serebrovsky. As a result of the experience, Dunn became a founder and active member of the American-Soviet Friendship Council and, during World War II, was the president of the American-Soviet Science Society. Deeply disturbed by the rise of Nazism, Dunn became an active member of the Emergency Committee for German Scholars (later called the Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced Scholars) in 1933, helping refugee scholars to relocate in American. Not surprisingly, Dunn's interest in international collaboration brought him under severe criticism. The organizations in which he took part were deemed subversive in the reactionary environment of the late 1940s and 1950s, and Dunn himself was accused of being a Communist.
Dunn's internationalism and interest in Russian science drew him into the Lysenko controversy of the 1950s. The "dictator" of Soviet biology during the Stalinist era and beyond, Lysenko espoused eccentric ideas about agriculture and genetics, and led a wholesale assault on modern genetics theories. The Russian language edition of Dunn's Principles of Genetics had sold more copies in Russian in the 1930s than the English original, however Lysenko banned the book.
Dunn pursued his interest in genetics to the end of his life. When he retired from Columbia in 1962, he was granted emeritus status and set up a "mouse lab" to continue work in collaboration with his former student, Dorothea Bennett. Toward the end of his life he developed an interest in the history of science, writing A Short History of Genetics in 1965. The donation of his papers to the American Philosophical Society helped to establish the APS archives as a premier facility for the study of the history of genetics.
Dunn was a member of the American Philosophical Society (1943), the National Academy of Sciences (1943), the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the Norwegian Academy of Sciences, and the Italian Academia Pataviana. He was a founder of the Genetics Society of America, its President in 1932, and managing editor of its journal, Genetics, from 1935 to 1940. He was also a member of the American Society of Naturalists, its President in 1960, and editor of its journal The American Naturalist, from 1951 to 1960. He was a member of the American Society of Human Genetics, and its President in 1961. He also was a visiting professor at the Genetics Institute of the University of Oslo, Norway in 1934-35, at the Instituto Superiore de Sanita, Rome, in 1953-54, and at University College, London in 1960-61.
African American History Note
Scholars of African American history will find interesting material in this collection on the subjects of race and biology, in particular in regards to Dunn's work with Theodosius Dobzhansky and Ashley Montagu.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Scholars of physiology, biochemistry, or biophysics may find the following of interest:
Stanley, Wendell M. (Wendell Meredith), 1904-1971 ( Located within American-Soviet Science Society (1945) correspondence and National Academy of Sciences (1943) correspondence.) Correspondence (2 items) 1943, 1945 English
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
American Committee for Displaced German Scholars Correspondence (Approximately 180 items) 1933-1937
American Philosophical Society Library Correspondence (8 folders) 1961-1972
American Philosophical Society Seminars Correspondence (2 folders) 1967-1969
American-Soviet Friendship Council Correspondence (2 folders) 1944-1948
American-Soviet Science Society Correspondence (3 folders) 1945-1947
Atomic Energy Commission Records (18 folders) 1960-1972
Bonnevie, Kristine Correspondence (36 items) 1930-1938
Brecher, Leonore Correspondence (29 items) 1930-1938
Bridges, Calvin B. Correspondence (40 items) 1932-1940
British scientists Correspondence (26 items) 1940
Carrel, Alexis Correspondence (95 items) 1923-1936
Caspari, Ernst Wilhelm Correspondence (57 items) 1938-1944
Castle, William Ernest Correspondence (97 items) 1924-1961
Charles, Donald Randolph Correspondence (22 items) 1930-1955
Columbia University Correspondence (18 folders) 1929-1945
Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station Correspondence (21 items) 1928-1933
Dahlberg, Gunnar Correspondence (56 items) 1946-1957
Danforth, Charles Haskell Correspondence (45 items) 1928-1952
David, Paul R. Correspondence (28 items) 1930-1946
Demerec, Milislav Correspondence (25 items) 1936-1951
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Correspondence (353 items) 1936-1951
Dunn, Leslie Clarence Manuscripts (51 folders) 1915-1960
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- James Island, S.C. studies Records (11 folders) 1955-1957
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- Lectures Correspondence (13 folders) 1950-1959
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- Oral History Records, Oral history interview transcripts Records (1 linear foot) 1958-1960
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- Photographs Photographs (2 boxes) 1911-1974
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- Refugees Correspondence (5 folders) 1929-1942
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- Rome, Jewish Community Records (30 folders) 1953-1956
Dunn, Leslie Clarence -- Science in the U.S.S.R. Correspondence (91 items) 1944-1952
Edwards, Marvin L. Correspondence (140 items) 1953-1954
Ephrussi, Boris Correspondence (25 items) 1932-1941
Fackenthal, Frank D. Correspondence (33 items) 1940-1949
Fisher, Ronald Aylmer Correspondence (32 items) 1928-1957
Genetics Correspondence (52 folders) 1935-1941
Genetics Society of America Correspondence (97 items) 1928-1934
Gerould, John H. Correspondence (14 items) 1919-1955
Goldschmidt, Richard Benedict Correspondence (80 items) 1928-1950
Gruneberg, Hans Correspondence (79 items) 1937-1955
Huxley, Julian Correspondence (36 items) 1930-1961
Iltis, Hugo Correspondence (215 items) 1938-1956
International Congress of Genetics. Seventh Congress Correspondence (66 items) 1935-1939
Ivanyi, Pavol Correspondence (64 items) 1967-1970
Jollos, Victor Correspondence (35 items) 1967-1970
Journal of Heredity Correspondence (47 items) 1928-1933
Kilgore Bill Correspondence (78 items) 1943-1950
Landauer, Walter Correspondence (1,080 items) 1924-1974
Landsteiner, Karl Correspondence (53 items) 1924-1932
Lewontin, Richard Charles Correspondence (28 items) 1959-1973
Lippincott, William A. Correspondence (71 items) 1921-1927
Little, Clarence Cook Correspondence (30 items) 1928-1941
Lydenberg, Harry Miller Correspondence (25 items) 1938-1941
Lysenko Controversy in the U. S. Correspondence (61 items) 1945-1949
McGraw-Hill Book Company Correspondence (92 items) 1931-1969
Mohr, Otto Louis Correspondence (76 items) 1929-1967
Morgan, Thomas Hunt Correspondence (21 items) 1918-1945
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (61 items) 1928-1967
National Academy of Sciences Correspondence (48 items) 1943-1972
National Research Council. Committee on experimental animals and plants Correspondence (175 items) 1928-1932
New American Library Correspondence (4 folders) 1957-1971
Oehlkers, Friedrich Correspondence (39 items) 1938-1939
Rizki, Tahir Mirza Correspondence (38 items) 1948-1970
Snell, George D. Correspondence (34 items) 1939-1972
United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO) Correspondence (78 items) 1950-1952
University Federation for Intellectual Freedom Correspondence (3 folders) 1937-1939
U.S.S.R. Geneticists Correspondence (104 items) 1928-1946
Whiting, Phineas W. Correspondence (28 items) 1920-1940
Wright, Sewall Correspondence (30 items) 1920-1964
Yanagisawa, Kaichiro Correspondence (4 folders) 1962-1973
American-Soviet Friendship Council; American-Soviet Science Society.; Bjerknes, Kristian Bonnevie, 1901-; Blakeslee, Albert Francis,1874-1954.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942; Bonnevie, Kristine; Bridges, Calvin B. (Calvin Blackman), 1889-1938; Carrel, Alexis, 1873-1944; Caspari, Ernst W.; Castle, William E., (William Ernest), 1867-1962; Cohn, Alfred E., (Alfred Einstein), 1879-1957; Columbia University.; Corner, George Washington, 1889-1981; Dahlberg, Gunnar, 1893-1956; Danforth, Charles H., (Charles Haskell), b. 1883; David, Paul R.; Demerec, M., (Milislav), 1895-1966; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975; Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced German Scholars; Ephrussi, Boris, 1901-1979; Fisher, Ronald Aylmer, Sir, 1890-1962; Geyer-Duszynska, Irene, 1924-; Goldschmidt, Richard; Gumbel, Emil J.; Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975; Iltis, Hugo; Ivanyi, Pavol; Jennings, H. S., (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947; Jollas, Victor; Landauer, Walter, 1896-; Landsteiner, Karl, 1868-1943; Lewontin, Richard Charles, 1929-; Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich, 1898-1976; Mohr, Otto Louis, 1886-; Mohr, Tove; Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; National Research Council. Committee on Experimental Animals and Plants; Stern, Curt, 1902-1981; Wilson, Edwin Bidwell, 1879-1964; Biology, genetics, eugenics; Developmental genetics; Drosophila--Genetics; Eugenics; Evolution (Biology); Geneticists; Genetics; Heredity; Italy--Population studies; Jews--Population studies; Jews--Rome; Lectures; Mice--Genetics; Notebooks; Photoprints; Political refugees--United States; Popuation biology; Poultry--Genetics; Race, race relations, racism; Science and politics
- Series I. Correspondence, ca.1920-1974 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  The scientific and professional correspondence of L.C Dunn provides a remarkable overview of the developments in genetic theory and research from the days of Morgan's fly lab into the molecular revolution of the 1950s and 1960s. Possessed of a sharp historical consciousness, Dunn appears to have been unusually good about retaining correspondence with his colleagues, and the resultant collection
  The Dunn Papers are further valuable as a point of entry into the debates over the social implications of genetic thought in an international context. An activist, Dunn was heavily involved in the American Committee for Displaced German Scholars during the 1930s, the America-Soviet Science Society, and the American-Soviet Friendship Council, among other organizations. His surviving essays and lectures (filed under Dunn) frequently address the social aspects of genetics, whether discussing eugenics, the "race problem," Lysenkoism ("Science Under Socialism," "Soviet Genetics") or broader issues of heredity and environment.
  In 1972 (1972-622ms) and 1974 (1974-454ms) and previously, Walter Landauer donated an extensive body of his correspondence with Dunn, which has been integrated into the collection. This correspondence was restricted during Dunn's lifetime, but is now open to researchers.
  - Adelman, Adrien (Box 1)
  - Alfert, Max (Box 1)
  - Altenbert, Edgar (Box 1)
  - American Anthropologist - Notes (Box 1)
  - American Association of Scientific Workers (Box 1)
    Melba Phillips in re: arrest of Ralph Spitzer
  - American Cancer Society (Box 1)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (Box 1)
  - American Committee for Democracy and Intellectual Freedom (Box 1)
  - American Committee for Displaced German Scholars, 1933-1937; Approximately 180 items (Box 1)
    Bagster-Collins, E.W.
    Bluhm, Agnes
    Burns, Arthur R.
    Blakeslee, A.F.
    Braun, Werner
    Crouch, Mary
    Clarke, Hans T.
    Danforth, C.H.
    Dowd, Agnes M.
    Duggan, Stephen P.
    Emerson, R.A.
    Farrand, Livingston
    Fuchs
    Goldschmidt, Richard
    Gregg, Allan
    Griswold, Lura
    Grueneberg, Hans
    Gruger, Franz
    Gudernatsch, F.
    Harrison, Ross G.
    Hayden, Philip M.
    Heichelheim, Fritz
    Hirsch
    Jacobson, Werner
    Kallius
    Kühn, A.
    Landauer, Walter
    Lydenberg, Harry M.
    McClintoch, Barbara
    Macmillan, Kerr D.
    Mitchell, Wesley C.
    MC6llendorff, Prof. von
    Moore, Carl R.
    Murrow, Edward R.
    Perlsee, Hanne
    Potter, Russell
    Schneebeli, Max H.
    Shull, A. Franklin
    Snyder, Laurence H.
    Spemann, H.
    Stern, Curt
    Stout, A.B.
    Timofeeff-Ressovsky, N.W.
    Ubisch, Gerda von
    Weaver, Warren
    Westermann, William
    Whiting, P.W.
    Wilbur, Ray Lyman
    Willier, B.H.
    Wright, Sewall